A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6 FA278
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
1923-1929
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund
FA278
0.69 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
Scope and Contents note
An outgrowth of the Commonwealth Fund's relief activities in Eastern and Central Europe after World War I, the Austrian Program provided vital help in improving the health of children in Austria. From 1923 until 1929 the CF maintained an office in Vienna, and conducted a program of health and preventive medicine for children. Child health demonstrations were conducted in Salzburg, and similar activities transpired in Vienna, Klagenfurt, Graz, and elsewhere.
Emphasis was placed on bettering the Austrian type of health service, rather than the introduction of American methods. Additional educational training was provided through fellowships. Austrian support for the program was gradually increased, and by 1929 sufficient success and stability had been attained to ensure continuance of the work without Commonwealth Fund support.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Public health; Public welfare; United States; War relief; Child psychology; Child mental health; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Hygiene; Law; Child welfare; Education, Rural; Medical education; Medical research; Legal issues; Legal research; Mental health; Medicine, Rural; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Yale University; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Social Science Research Council; Harvard University; Columbia University; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Charles W.
- Administrative Policies, 1923-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Audits and Correspondence, March 3, 1926-July 23, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Budget, July 1926-June 1927 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Budget, July 1927-June 1928 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Budget, July 1928-June 1929 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Expenditures, July 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Financial Correspondence, June 8, 1923-December 20, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Financial Correspondence, January 13, 1927-June 8, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Financial Statements - Austria, July 1923 to June 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Financial Statements - Austria, July 1925 to June 1926 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Financial Statements - Austria, July 1926 to June 1927 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Financial Statements - Austria, July 1927 to June 1928 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Financial Statements - Austria, July 1928 to June 1929 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Financial Statements - New York, June 1923 to June 1925 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Financial Statements - New York, July 1925 to June 1926 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Financial Statements - New York, July 1926 to June 1927 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Financial Statements - New York, July 1927 to June 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Financial Statements - New York, July 1928 to June 1929 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- General Austrian Financial and Economic Information, March 4, 1924-July 5, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 19)